Richard J. Powell
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Richard J. Powell papers
1971-1992
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Powell, Richard J.
1.0 linear foot
The Richard J. Powell papers date from 1971 through 1992 and mostly concern Powell's research and writings on painter William H. Johnson. Found is correspondence with curators, scholors, arts administrators, and U.S., Danish, and Scandinavian museums and associations. The papers also include two of Powell's illustrated research and travel journals from 1984 and 1985, printed materials concerning the exhibition Powell curated in 1991 at the National Museum of American Art Homecoming: William H. Johnson and Afro-America, 1938-1946, research files that contain photocopies of original Johnson archival documents from various research repositories, and photographs (copy prints) of Johnson and his artwork.
Biographical Note
Art historian, Durham, North Carolina. Powell curated the exhibition Homecoming: William H. Johnson and Afro-America, 1938-1946, at the National Museum of American Art, 1991-1992.
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1980-1992, mostly concerning art historian Richard Powell's research and writings on painter William H. Johnson (1901-1970). Found is Powell's correspondence with Robert Baehr, Sigrid Bondo, Adelyn Breeskin, David C. Driskell, Michel Fabre, Robert Ferris Thompson, Øystein Hjort, Margo Humphrey, Gregers Krake, Richard A. Long, Torben Lundbæk, Virginia Mecklenburg, Jostein Nerbøvik, Mette Nørredam, James Parker, Jules D. Prown, Kjetil Tandstad, Judith Wilson, Debbie Wood, and Danish and Scandinavian museums and associations. There are also two illustrated research/travel journals containing Powell's comments on Johnson's works of art, related thoughts, slide lists, notes from his lectures at the Sorbonne in Paris, and other experiences dating from July 14 to November 28, 1984, and January 1 to June 20, 1985; two wall calendars, 1984-1985, noting appointments and exhibition openings; a notebook, loose notes and other writings; postcards, reseach files that contain photocopies of printed material and other primary documents about Johnson including clippings from foreign newspapers with translations; printed material concerning the exhibition Homecoming: William H. Johnson and Afro-America, 1938-1946, curated by Powell at the National Museum of American Art, 1991-1992; photographs (copy prints, contact prints, and negatives) of Johnson and his artwork; and miscellany.
Arrangement
Series 1: Research and Project Correspondence, 1981-1991(Box 1; 19 folders)
Series 2: Travel and Research Journals and Notes, 1984-1985, 1991, undated (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 3: Printed Material, 1971-1992, undated (Box 1; 9 folders)
Series 4: Research Files, undated (Box 1; 10 folders)
Series 5: Photographs and Negatives, undated (Box 1; 4 folders)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms.
Subjects:
Johnson, William H., 1901-1970
Subjects-Topical:
African American artists -- Exhibitions; Art historians -- Washington (D.C.); African American artists
Types of Materials:
Travel journals
Provenance
Richard Powell collected this material while conducting research on William H. Johnson. He donated it to the Archives of American Art in July, 2000.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Research and Project Correspondence, 1981-1991, Series 1:; (Box 1; 19 folders)
  Correspondence concerning Powell's travels, his research, dissertation, and exhibition planning. Correspondents include Robert Baehr, Sigrid Bondo, Adelyn Breeskin, David C. Driskell, Michel Fabre, Robert Ferris Thompson, Øystein Hjort, Margo Humphrey, Gregers Krake, Richard A. Long, Torben Lundbæk, Virginia Mecklenburg, Jostein Nerbøvik, Mette Nørredam, James Parker, Jules D. Prown, Kjetil Tandstad, Judith Wilson, Debbie Wood, and Danish and Scandinavian museums and associations.
  - Early Correspondence, 1981-1983 (Box 1)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1984-1991, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding William H. Johnson Monograph and Research, 1985-1991 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Dissertation, 1986-1988 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Contacts in Denmark and Norway, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Residency Permit in Denmark, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Contacts in the U.S., 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Fulbright Grant, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Lectures in Europe, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Travel Arrangements, 1984-1985, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence regarding Research (includes research notes), 1984-1991, (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Proposal for Book and Exhibition, circa 1989 (Box 1)
- Travel and Research Journals and Notes, 1984-1985, 1991, undated, Series 2:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  Found are two illustrated research/travel journals containing Powell's comments on Johnson's works of art, related thoughts, slide lists, notes from his lectures at the Sorbonne in Paris, and other experiences dating from July 14 to November 28, 1984, and January 1 to June 20, 1985; two wall calendars, 1984-1985, noting appointments and exhibition openings; a notebook, loose notes and other writings.
  - Travel and Research Journals, 1984-1985, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Research Notebook, circa 1989 (Box 1)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1)
  - Calendars, 1984-1985 (Box 1)
- Printed Material, 1971-1992, undated, Series 3:; (Box 1; 9 folders)
  Found are photocopies of printed materials, as well as magazine and newspaper clippings, and postcards.
  - Postcards, undated (Box 1)
  - Printed Materials, 1971-1992, (8 folders) (Box 1)
- Research Files on William H. Johnson, undated, Series 4:; (Box 1; 10 folders)
  Research files composed by Powell concerning William H. Johnson and family. Files contain mixed printed materials and numerous photocopies from archival research repositories.
  - Research Files, undated, (10 folders) (Box 1)
- Photographs and Negatives, undated, Series 5:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  Photographs (copy prints, contact prints, and negatives) of William H. Johnson and his artwork.
  - Photographs of William H. Johnson and his Artwork, undated, (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 1)